Guide to the Watson Smith Rankin Papers, 1911-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Watson Smith Rankin papers 1911-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rankin, Watson S. (Watson Smith), 1879-1970.
7.6 linear feet Extent: 10,729 Items
Professor of pathology; Dean of Wake Forest Medical School; Secretary of the N.C. State Board of Health; Director of the Hospital and Orphan Section of the Duke Endowment. Correspondence, legal and financial papers, memorabilia, speeches, clippings, printed materials, photographs, and a diary, all relating to the life and career of Dr. Watson Smith Rankin. Correspondence is chiefly between Dr. Rankin and his son, Jesse, friends and other relatives, and professional colleagues; much of the material concerns administrative aspects of medicine related to the Duke Endowment and the State Board of Health. Many of the writings, lectures, and speeches discuss hospital reform, and some concern philosophical and religious issues. There are also financial papers and biographical information. Also includes a 1932 report by the Commission on the Costs of Medical Care, entitled "An outline program of medical care for the People of the United States."
RL.01068
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Watson Smith Rankin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1971.
Biographical Note
Watson smith Rankin was a Professor of Pathology; Dean of Wake Forest Medical School; Secretary of the N.C. State Board of Health; and Director of the Hospital and Orphan Section of the Duke Endowment.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, legal and financial papers, memorabilia, speeches, clippings, printed materials, photographs, and a diary, all relating to the life and career of Dr. Watson Smith Rankin. Correspondence is chiefly between Dr. Rankin and his son, Jesse, friends and other relatives, and professional colleagues; much of the material concerns administrative aspects of medicine related to the Duke Endowment and the State Board of Health. Many of the writings, lectures, and speeches discuss hospital reform, and some concern philosophical and religious issues. Financial papers record stock transactions, salaries, taxes, and philanthropic activities of Dr. Rankin. There are also several transcripts of interviews which provide biographical details. Other items include a diary entitled "Of official relations to the Methodist Home," photographs of the Duke Endowment trustees and of several N.C. governors, and Rankin's writings on Dr. John Atkinson Ferrell, who served in the Rockefeller Foundation's health division. Also includes a 1932 report by the Commission on the Costs of Medical Care, entitled "An outline program of medical care for the People of the United States."
Subject Headings
Rankin, Jesse; Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson), 1880-1965; Duke Endowment. Hospital and Orphan Section; North Carolina. State Board of Health; Physicians -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Hospitals -- Administration; Medical care -- North Carolina -- History; Medical care -- United States -- History; North Carolina -- History
Detailed Description of Collection
- Watson S. Rankin Papers, 1911-1970, (19 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1928 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1932 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1939 Aug. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1939 Sept.-1942 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1951 Sept. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1951 Oct.-1956 Mar. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1956 Apr.-1960 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1964 May (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1964 June-1970 (Box 11)
  - Writings, 1911-1949 (Box 12)
  - Writings, 1952-1967 (Box 13)
  - Speeches, 1927-1949 (Box 13)
  - Bergson-Gifford Lectures (Box 14)
  - Hocking-Tillich Lectures (Box 15)
  - Writings and speeches by others, 1911-1970 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1932-1970 (Box 16)
  - Financial papers (Box 17)
  - Legal papers (Box 17)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 17)
  - Genealogy (Box 17)
  - Photographs (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook (Box 18)
  - Duke Endowment album, 1964 (Box 19)
  - Oversize materials (Opaperfolder 1-2)